José Jair Santanna

Enthusiastic, Researcher, Lecturer, Network Security Specialist & (Big) Data Analyst

Contact

Drienerlolaan 5, Zilverling 5110, 7522 NB Enschede, The Netherlands.

+31 (6) 42330703

http://jairsantanna.com j.i.santanna@utwente.nl

Languages

portuguese native english fluency spanish comprehension dutch comprehension

Programming

Bash, Python, C#,SQL PIG, Spark & Impala

Professional Objective

I am currently a PhD candidate at University of Twente (ending in 2017) in a research group called Design and Analysis of Communication Systems (DACS). My research is founded by the European commission via a project focus in network of excellence, called Flamingo. In addition, my research is funded by one of the main Dutch national Organisation for Scientific Research (NWO) in a project called Distributed Denial of Service Defence (D3).

I am interested in a research & development position with focus on network security and the use of big data technologies to improve network data analysis. A position where I can transfer my enthusiasm, knowledge, skills and experience into meaningful innovation to improve the security in computer networks, specially in the Internet.

Education

2013-Now **Doctor** in Computer Science University of Twente, The Netherlands

"The DDoS as a \$ervice Phenomenon". Supervisor: Prof. dr. ir. Aiko Pras

2010–2012 Master in Computer Science Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil

"A BPM-based Solution for Inter-domain Circuit Management". The outcome of this work generated a product still in use by the Brazilian National Education and Research Network (RNP) (Link: http://meican.cipo.rnp.br/).

Supervisor: Prof. dr. Lisandro Zambenedetti Granville

2005–2010 **Bachelor** in Computer Engineer Federal University of Pará, Brazil

"A Comparative Evaluation of DCCP Protocol in Mesh Networks."

Supervisor: Dr. Kelvin Lopes Dias

Experience

Technical Adviser

2016 To the Yokohama National University Japan

For the production of a report on "Reflection & Amplification DDoS attacks" requested by the *Japanese Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications*.

2016 To the Dutch National Cyber Security Center and the Scientific Research & Documen-

tion Center The Netherlands

For the production of a report on "Cyber metrics 2016: DDoS and Malware" requested by the *Dutch Ministry of Security and Justice*.

Assistant Professor

2012–2013 University of Santa Cruz do Sul (UNISC)

Santa Cruz do Sul, Brazil

Tasks & Responsibilities: Supervise students and teach the following courses: Computer Networks, Computer Network Management, and Digital Systems.

Guest Lecturer

2015 & 2016 **Product Design to Online Business (course)**University of Twente, The Netherlands
Audience: bachelor students of industrial engineering and business information

technology.

2015 **Network Security (course)** University of Twente, The Netherlands

Audience: master and bachelor students of computer science, electrical engineer, and telematics from the University of Twente, 3TU cyber security, and

members of ICT labs.

2015 **Cybercrime & Cybersecurity (minor)** University of Twente, The Netherlands

Audience: bachelor students from University of Twente, European Research Center for Information (ERCIS), Westfälische Wilhelms - Univerität Münster, Uni-

versität Innsbruck, and University of Leicester.

Student Supervisor

Among 10 supervised students: 5 decided to follow towards the next academic degree[↑], PhD or MSc, 2 received the MSc degree cum laude[♦], 2 won the best paper award in international conferences[*], and 1 won the second place of a renowned Dutch national prize (KIVI/Defensie & Veiligheid) for her thesis[*].

[M.Sc. Degree]Justyna Chromik[$^{\uparrow}$ $^{\diamond}$ *], Wouter de Vries[$^{\uparrow}$ *], Joey de Vries[$^{\Diamond}$], Mark Wierbosch, and Jarmo van Lenthe.

[B.Sc. Degree] Roeland Krak[†], Max Kerkers[†], Dirk Maan[†], Jochum Börger, and Guilherme Dressler.

International Conference Reviewer

The first four listed conferences are among the top well ranked related to the Committee on Network Operation and Management (CNOM), which is a renowned technical committee part of the IEEE Communications Society. For each conference we present the acronym, the full name, the acceptance rate of paper submitted divided by published* (according www.cs.ucsb.edu/~almeroth), and the h-index* (according Google scholar).

CNSM	International Conference on Network and Service Management	17.6% 18
NETWORKIN	GIFIP Networking	23.8% 22
IM	IFIP/IEEE Integrated Management	27.2% 18
NOMS	IEEE/IFIP Network Operations and Management Symposium	28.9% 22
AIMS	Autonomous Infrastructure, Management and Security	31.8% 9
SCC	IEEE Symposium on Computers and Communications	46.4% 20
APNOMS	Asia-Pacific Network Operations and Management Symposium	- 10

*last checked: April 7,2016

Software Developer

2015-Now Distributed Denial of Service Attacks Database (DDoSDB)

Link: http://www.ddosdb.net

An initiative to develop the largest open database with DDoS attacks.

Languages: Python, Bash, Pig Latin & Apache Impala

2010–2011 Management Environment of Inter-domain Circuits for Advanced Networks (MEICAN)

Link: http://meican.cipo.rnp.br/

Development of an Executable Network Management Policies Editor sponsored

by the Brazilian National Education and Research Network (RNP).

Language: WS-BPEL

2009 Support for Planning Sustainable Electrical Power Generation via Vegetable Oil.

Desktop application part of a Ph.D. thesis [link] sponsored by a subsidiary

(Eletronorte) of the major Brazilian power utility (Eletrobrás).

Language: C#.Net & mySQL

Presentations

More than 30 presentations in the last 3 years (available on my slideshare.net/jjcsantanna), among those I highlight:

2015	Oral Presentation	at Logius (part of the Dutch Ministry of the Interior and Kingdom Relations).
2015	Oral Presentation t	to the Dutch National Management Organization of Internet Providers (NBIP).
2015	Oral Presentation	to the Dutch National Cyber Security Centrum (NCSC).
2013 & 2015	Oral Presentation	at the 31 th and 36 th IRTF Network Management Research Group (NMRG).

Awards

2015	Best Ph.D. 'Elevator Pitch' (1 st	Place) CTIT Symposium, University of Twente
2015	Best Poster (3 rd Place)	CTIT Symposium, University of Twente
2015	Best Paper Award Autor	nomous Infrastructure, Management and Security Conference
2015	Top Papers Nomination Brazilian	Symposium on Computer Networks and Distributed Systems
2010	Student Award (3 rd Place)	Computer Engineer, Federal University of Pará, Brazil

CV last update: April 7, 2016

Scientific Appendix

Publications

DDoS 3.0 - How Terrorists Bring Down the Internet

Aiko Pras, José Jair Santanna, Jessica Steinberger, Anna Sperotto International GI/ITG Conference, MMB & DFT, 2016

Booter websites characterization: Towards a list of threats

Justyna Joanna Chromik, José Jair Santanna, Anna Sperotto, Aiko Pras Brazilian Symposium on Computer Networks and Distributed Systems (SBRC), 2015

Inside Booters: An Analysis on Operational Databases

José Jair Santanna, Romain Durban, Anna Sperotto, Aiko Pras IFIP/IEEE International Symposium on Integrated Network Management (IM), 2015

Booters - An Analysis of DDoS-as-a-Service Attacks.

José Jair Santanna, Roland Rijswijk-Deij, Anna Sperotto, Rick Hofstede, Mark Wierbosch, Lisandro Zambenedetti Granville, Aiko Pras

IFIP/IEEE International Symposium on Integrated Network Management (IM), 2015

How Asymmetric Is the Internet? A Study to Support the Use of Traceroute

Wouter Vries, José Jair Santanna, Anna Sperotto, Aiko Pras

International Conference on Autonomous Infrastructure, Management and Security (AIMS), 2015

Characterisation of the Kelihos.B Botnet

Max Kerkers, José Jair Santanna, Anna Sperotto

International Conference on Autonomous Infrastructure, Management and Security (AIMS), 2014

Towards Validation of the Internet Census 2012

Dirk Maan, José Jair Santanna, Anna Sperotto, Pieter-Tjerk Boer EUNICE/IFIP International Workshop (EUNICE), 2014

Characterizing and Mitigating The DDoS-as-a-Service Phenomenon

José Jair Santanna, Anna Sperotto

International Conference on Autonomous Infrastructure, Management and Security (AIMS), 2014

Through the Internet of Things - A Management by Delegation Smart Object Aware System (MbDSAS)

Marcelo Marotta, Felipe Carbone, José Jair Santanna, Liane Tarouco IEEE Computer Software and Applications Conference (COMPSAC), 2013

A BPM-based solution for inter-domain circuit management

José Jair Santanna, Juliano Wickboldt, Lisandro Zambenedetti Granville IEEE Network Operations and Management Symposium (NOMS), 2012

Internet of Things in healthcare: Interoperatibility and security issues

Liane Tarouco, Leandro Bertholdo, Lisandro Zambenedetti Granville, Lucas Arbiza, Marcelo Marotta, José Jair Santanna

IEEE International Conference on Communications (ICC), 2012